<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Process on mixmix</title><link>https://mixmix.nz/tags/process/</link><description>Recent content in Process on mixmix</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://mixmix.nz/tags/process/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Lemons 🍋🍋🍋</title><link>https://mixmix.nz/p/lemons/</link><pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mixmix.nz/p/lemons/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/lemons/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Lemons 🍋🍋🍋" />&lt;p>&lt;em>Originally published on Scuttlebutt in 2018. Additional section added with
updated learnings.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When I was a teacher I worked with this guy Pete Brailsford, who taught
mountaineering. He&amp;rsquo;d take students up into the snow and build snow caves to
sleep in overnight, cross rivers, stuff like that. A major part of the learning
in that context was about &lt;em>managing risks&lt;/em>. The idea is that you can&amp;rsquo;t control
everything, but you can keep an eye on the probability field you&amp;rsquo;re standing
in.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/lemons/pete_tramping.jpeg"
width="944"
height="693"
srcset="https://mixmix.nz/p/lemons/pete_tramping_hu_6e9ebf5012e122b4.jpeg 480w, https://mixmix.nz/p/lemons/pete_tramping_hu_9ff6a97729e9ebec.jpeg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Pete Brailsford Tramping"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="136"
data-flex-basis="326px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He talked about it like a slot machine - those ones where you pull the handle
and then the options spin and then they lock in like:&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="cherries-lemon-cherries-cherries-green_apple">&amp;#x1f352; &amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x1f352; &amp;#x1f352; &amp;#x1f34f;
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>Normally if you get all cherries or something, it&amp;rsquo;s a jackpot, but in this
story, if you get a row of lemons, that&amp;rsquo;s bad, like &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;you got hypothermia and
no-one knows where you are&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em> bad.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So you can&amp;rsquo;t control all the slots, but you can watch where you&amp;rsquo;re at. Say you
set out on our adventure, the slots are spinning, and you know what, someone in
our group forgot their jacket &lt;em>BOOM&lt;/em> the first slot just came up&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="lemon-white_large_square-white_large_square-white_large_square-white_large_square">&amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x2b1c; &amp;#x2b1c; &amp;#x2b1c; &amp;#x2b1c;
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>Ok it&amp;rsquo;s a lemon, but no big deal, it&amp;rsquo;s sunny as. You stop and have lunch,
there&amp;rsquo;s some clouds on the horizon, but it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em>so warm&lt;/em>. Guess what you just
missed a hint, and as you continue to walk it starts to rain and a wind picks
up (being a small island in a massive ocean, weather can change &lt;em>very&lt;/em> quickly
in nz) &amp;hellip; now you&amp;rsquo;ve got 2 lemons&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="lemon-lemon-white_large_square-white_large_square-white_large_square">&amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x2b1c; &amp;#x2b1c; &amp;#x2b1c;
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>Again this is not that big a deal&amp;hellip; except you already have that 1 lemon, so
now you&amp;rsquo;ve got someone in your group who&amp;rsquo;s getting cold. I guess you can see the
trend. Any one of these things is no big deal, but a series of little
misfortunes have a &lt;em>cummulative&lt;/em> effect in terms of the odds you&amp;rsquo;re playing
with. So if you&amp;rsquo;re in this position&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="lemon-lemon-lemon-lemon-white_large_square">&amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x2b1c;
&lt;/h1>&lt;p>You&amp;rsquo;re now playing a very high stakes games, where one more little lemon, like a
sprained ankle can tip you over into disaster.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="how-to-manage-lemons">How to manage lemons
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Lemons aren&amp;rsquo;t always avoidable, but you can often plan ahead and consider what
the odds of lemons are based on different paths. Further, you can reflect as
situtations evolve, asking yourself:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>How many lemons are we currently at?&lt;/p>&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Just having this self-reflective question in your toolbelt can change how you
think and see. It can be really hard to spot them because they can often be
innocuous in the context where they first present &amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s just &lt;em>in concert&lt;/em>
that the the real trouble manifests. Asking this question out loud to yourself
and your questing party can help you spot more of them early, as well as
increase the liklihood you&amp;rsquo;ll keep them in working memory (most humans suck at
remembering many small factors).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you spot yourself crossing 3-4 lemons, you should probably be starting to
significantly re-asses your plans. Things like:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>abort&lt;/strong>: ask yourself if your initial plan is still safe&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>simplify&lt;/strong>: consider cutting non-vital parts of your plan&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>alert&lt;/strong>: increase new-lemon vigilance, prepare to escalate responses faster&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="but-mix-im-not-a-mountaineer">But mix, I&amp;rsquo;m not a mountaineer
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>This is relevant to anyone on any adventure (solo, or as a team). You could be
voyaging into literal moutains, or sailing to Great Barrier Island, or you could
be a distributed team building FOSS tools on a limited / no budget.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some lemons that have fucked up quests I&amp;rsquo;ve been on:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>having no retrosepctives (process for iterating, adaptation)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>just trusting that everyone remembers the agreement we made &lt;em>(contracts, pay,
expectations)&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>forgetting to ask how people are feeling&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;figuring it out later&amp;rdquo; for onboarding / offboarding / holidays / sick leave&lt;/li>
&lt;li>not telling each other vital quest-changing info &lt;em>(assuming mind-reading or
avoiding conflict)&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>being unclear on who&amp;rsquo;s doing what&lt;/li>
&lt;li>using too many different tools for communication / coordination&lt;/li>
&lt;li>being unclear about ownership / responsibility&lt;/li>
&lt;li>saying &amp;ldquo;this is a flat strucutre, everyone is equal&amp;rdquo; (but not actually doing
anything to actively distribute power)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>forgetting to account for how disruptive travel can be&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Sometimes the course you take has known lemons. Like it&amp;rsquo;s hard to set up
&lt;em>holiday pay&lt;/em> processes when you&amp;rsquo;re a small company and you know everyone and
you&amp;rsquo;re doing it for love and there are so many things to do. You just need to
acknowledge (and remember) that you&amp;rsquo;re carrying a lemon, and if you then try to
onboard someone new, you need to adjust your plan by either stopping to build
that missing stuff (unloading the lemon), or communicating to the new person
clearly about the known lemon.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="lemons-in-family-systems">Lemons in family systems
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>UPDATE: &lt;em>I&amp;rsquo;ve added this section because it&amp;rsquo;s how I&amp;rsquo;ve most used this
personally, and why I reference this pattern so often.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When I say &amp;ldquo;family system&amp;rdquo;, I mean any group of people very strongly committed
to supporting one another, such that the wellbeing of any one person in the
system &lt;em>strongly&lt;/em> effects the wellbeing of the system as a whole.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Examples of family systems I&amp;rsquo;ve seen that this is relevant for:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>parent(s) with kid(s)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>partners where at least one has a disability&lt;/li>
&lt;li>partners where at least one has mental health challenges&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>You know if you&amp;rsquo;re in such a family system when e.g. one of you gets sick, and
the experience is like &lt;em>the family is sick&lt;/em>. The arc of recovery is often slower
too, because of the complex interactions involved in one person getting taken
out.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="noticing-lemons">Noticing lemons
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>We don&amp;rsquo;t track lemons all the time in our family. Lemons in themselves are not
bad &amp;hellip; unattended compounding lemons tend towards disaster though. Typically we
start engaging this pattern when we notice ourselves generally &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>unreasonably&lt;/em> stressed&amp;rdquo;,
&amp;ldquo;&lt;em>a bit&lt;/em> overwhelmed&amp;rdquo;, or even just &amp;ldquo;unproductive&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The next step is to &lt;strong>pause&lt;/strong> and name the lemons we can spot. I&amp;rsquo;m feeling a bit
overwhelmed today, so here&amp;rsquo;s an example:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&amp;#x1f34b; work &amp;ndash; my work is in transition, lots of uncertainty&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;#x1f34b; community &amp;ndash; my school picnic got quagmired, lots of painful learning&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;#x1f34b; health &amp;ndash; I&amp;rsquo;ve had a low level cold for 2 weeks, have had a few nights
of bad sleep&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;hellip;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Okeee, so we&amp;rsquo;re at 3 lemons already, and that&amp;rsquo;s only counting the complexities
I&amp;rsquo;m holding&amp;hellip; No wonder I&amp;rsquo;m feeling a bit overwhelmed!&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="compassion">Compassion
&lt;/h3>&lt;p>Even noticing that you&amp;rsquo;ve carrying a bunch of lemons can be transformative. My
first step is usually to laugh a little, and feel a little bit of relief &amp;ndash; &lt;em>I&amp;rsquo;m
not useless, we have a lot on!&lt;/em> &amp;#x1f605;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Having some compassion for ourselves can immediately unload shame / guilt /
pressure, which is &lt;strong>very&lt;/strong> strategic, because:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>you just cut a meta-lemon (wasting brain cycles beating yourself up)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>you likely have less of a white-knuckle death-grip on your initial plans,
making it easier to adapt to your actual reality&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="complexity-capacity-lemon-spoon">Complexity capacity &amp;#x1f34b; &amp;#x1f944;
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>Another pattern we use in our family is &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spoon_theory" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Spoon
Theory&lt;/a>. The core idea is that if
you&amp;rsquo;re living with some disability you may have very limited capacity, and that
we could model how much capacity people have with units of capacity, spoons
&amp;#x1f944; say. A person with very limited capacity might start the day with 8
spoons, and then have to ration their spoons over the day e.g. shower costs 1
spoon, commute to work costs 2 spoons etc). If you run out of spoons&amp;hellip; maybe
you cannot get home, maybe you can but end up in massive spoon-debt (goodbye
tmrw).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Expanding spoons from the individual (to collective capacity) and blending in
the lemons pattern, we can start to say things like &amp;ldquo;today we only have capacity
for 2 lemons&amp;rdquo;. Lemons here represent complexity which will incur spoons
(capacity) cost.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This feels kind because it acknowledges our current capacity, and helps us bound
expectations of how much complexity we can perhaps carry.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Concretely, while going to a kids birthday in the morning followed by a friends bbq
in the afternoon may seem easy, if we only have 4 spoons, and
this plan takes us to 0 spoon exactly&amp;hellip; that leaves no capacity for unforseen
lemons, which world put us in spoon deficit. Better to plan one just the one
activity and have spare capacity for curveballs and still be within safe
operating bounds.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This concept is also useful in the context of startups. Startups are typically
operating with very limited resources (spoons). Basic operations cost capacity
(spoons), and innovation tends to cost in unforseen complexity (lemons). To that
end it&amp;rsquo;s important not to innovate on too many fronts simultaneously. Examples of
things which incur complexity cost:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&amp;#x1f34b; &amp;ldquo;fancy&amp;rdquo; legal strucures - e.g. coop, foundation + for-profit symbiosis, &amp;hellip;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;#x1f34b; novel technologies - e.g. encrypted replicatable database&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;#x1f34b; ethical investment mechanisms - e.g. non-voting shares, redeemable preference shares, &amp;hellip;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;#x1f34b; world-spanning teams - e.g. NZ, EU, USA&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Group Smells</title><link>https://mixmix.nz/p/group-smells/</link><pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://mixmix.nz/p/group-smells/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://mixmix.nz/p/group-smells/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Group Smells" />&lt;p>As a programmer, part of my job is to spot &lt;em>‘code smells’&lt;/em>.
Like being alert for musky over-ripeness somewhere in your fridge, or unwanted acridity of burning plastic coming from your computer, smells hint that nearby, something is amiss, and it’s probably going to get worse.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In code it’s usually that you’ve used a pattern that seemed good when you started, but as you continue to add things, suddenly it gets volatile.
An everyday example would be running too many appliances off a multi-board.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Patterns of coding that lead to future instability we call anti-patterns.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Code smells are the whiffs that help us notice anti-patterns.
Naming them helps us spot vulnerabilities, avert catastrophes, and support an evolving discourse about best (and worst) practice.&lt;/p>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>My flatmate just came back from a conference where she was pulling her hair out because the way the group was working together was counter-productive.
It occurred to me that it would be useful to port anti-patterns into the group-work context.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I want to know what group-smells are.
Here’s a few we were able to name in my lounge just now:&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="cargo-cult-collaboration">Cargo-cult collaboration
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>A variant of Richard Feynman’s &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cargo_cult_science" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>cargo-cult science&lt;/a>, this is implementation of collaboration through shallow adoption of whatever latest buzzword. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>A classic example you might hear is people asserting “we’re a totally flat self-organised group”.
Self-organisation is a thing, but it doesn’t grow just anywhere.
There are certain conditions in which it tends to work well, and many in which it doesn’t&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Some smells to watch out for :&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>lack of clarity about where and how decision making is happening&lt;/li>
&lt;li>invitation to ‘be the change’ without any guidance/ support to do that&lt;/li>
&lt;li>no description of what or how self-organisation is going to occur&lt;/li>
&lt;li>founders deny their power and leadership&lt;/li>
&lt;li>not everyone feels empowered to intervene in group processes&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The anti-pattern :&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>you think you’re making space for an ecosystem to magically appear, but you forgot to resource it&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Where this anti-pattern can lead :&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>invisible power structures which priviledge some actors without them being aware of it&lt;/li>
&lt;li>emergent inside / outside groups&lt;/li>
&lt;li>poor communication systems that lead to distrust&lt;/li>
&lt;li>people taking on too many things and burning out&lt;/li>
&lt;li>white men dominating lots of things, women doing administrative roles&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Patterns which support self-organisation :&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>naming power / leadership roles that exist&lt;/li>
&lt;li>actively sharing roles around&lt;/li>
&lt;li>making decision making processes clear&lt;/li>
&lt;li>clear communication systems&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="talking-over-each-other">Talking over each other
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>This one is easy.
In the best case, everyone just cares a lot about the topic of conversation, and they’re excited to share what the conversation is bringing up for them.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Other smells you might notice :&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>2 people having a conversation, while everyone else watches&lt;/li>
&lt;li>anxiety about when you’re going to get to speak&lt;/li>
&lt;li>lots of loud people, no quiet people&lt;/li>
&lt;li>an old white guy opinion-fest&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The anti-pattern :&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>you’ve skipped an agreement about how you’re going to approach things, and conversation has defaulted to loudest / most dominant&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Where this anti-pattern can lead :&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>less listening&lt;/li>
&lt;li>less diverse opinion &lt;/li>
&lt;li>shallow analysis&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Patterns you might consider that help:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>appoint a facilitator&lt;/li>
&lt;li>introduce a rule (e.g.
talking stick, or you can only talk again after 2 other people have spoken)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>change the format (e.g.
split into smaller groups, get everyone to write thoughts on cards, go for a walking dialogue)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="miscy-meeting">Miscy meeting
&lt;/h2>&lt;p>&lt;em>(pronounced ‘misky’, *misc = miscellaneous,)&lt;/em>
There’s a bunch of you in a room talking about your project and raising relevant ideas.
The conversation energy is good, and you’re discussing all the things. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>This is a great space for combining ideas, exploring shared values, and connecting with each other.
If you were intending to run a discovery session, or a workshop, that&amp;rsquo;s great.
If you were expecting decisions and action, it might be worth checking whether you&amp;rsquo;re in a miscy meeting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You might smell:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>no-one recording any actions / agreements&lt;/li>
&lt;li>surprise at the topics being raised (lack of agreement about why you’ve met)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>topic drift / people changing topics annoyingly&lt;/li>
&lt;li>excited exploration of &lt;a class="link" href="http://www.newyorker.com/culture/cultural-comment/the-rabbit-hole-rabbit-hole" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>rabbit-holes&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>no clear ending to meeting&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The anti-pattern :&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>you haven’t agreed on what you’re actually doing, so you’re starting a range of things and doing them poorly or not at all. &lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Where this anti-pattern can lead :&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>massive waste of group time&lt;/li>
&lt;li>frustration when people remember agreements / actions differently in the next meeting &lt;/li>
&lt;li>more miscy meetings, gradual loss of momentum&lt;/li>
&lt;li>inability to unlock &lt;a class="link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continual_improvement_process" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>continuous improvement&lt;/a> / evolution&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Patterns for clearer meetings :&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>start by asking ‘what is the purpose of this meeting?’&lt;/li>
&lt;li>use an agenda, and refer back to that when needed&lt;/li>
&lt;li>record agreements / actions (and who is going to do them) and share &lt;/li>
&lt;li>call ‘rabbit hole’ when you smell one&lt;/li>
&lt;li>use some ‘meeting ending’ ritual (e.g.
a checkout-round) so everyone knows when you’re done and don’t auto-extend your meeting ad infinitum&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;hr>
&lt;p>These are just a sample of course.
Lets spot anti-patterns together and name them.
Lets spot group-smells and do better work together.
I’d love to hear of any common anti-patterns you’ve already named in your group work, please post them up.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>